<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>IN4391 Distributed Systems Notes on Nick Tehrany</title>
    <link>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4391-distributed-systems-notes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in IN4391 Distributed Systems Notes on Nick Tehrany</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4391-distributed-systems-notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Resource Management and Scheduling</title>
      <link>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4391-distributed-systems-notes/management/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4391-distributed-systems-notes/management/</guid>
      <description>Reading Material Before Lecture Google Borg Google Borg is a management system for clusters that run several hundreds of thousands of jobs from many different applications, on many different clusters with each having several thousands machines.
Resource Management in Cloud Clouds contain large quantities of shared resources that provide provide these to large pools of data and compting with a variety of different interfaces. An important part of cloud computing is resource management, as there only are finite resources available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional Requirements</title>
      <link>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4391-distributed-systems-notes/functionalrequirements/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4391-distributed-systems-notes/functionalrequirements/</guid>
      <description>Reading Material Before Lecture Remote Procedure Call (RPC) RPC allows one program to call a procedure (subroutine or method) in another address space than its own, typically on another system, without the programmer explicitly implementing this remote interaction but instead it is the same as if a local process would invoke some method, except now it comes from a non-local process.
Message Bus Since distributed systems rely on message passing between different systems for sharing of data, the message bus enables this with the addition of hotplugging systems to this at any point in time without affecting any other system.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4391-distributed-systems-notes/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4391-distributed-systems-notes/introduction/</guid>
      <description>What is the difference between parallel computing and distributed computing?
In parallel computing there typically is one job that is split into multiple tasks, which are then split up to different cores/threads that run simultaneously. Such systems typically are homogenous, the hardware is all the same, i.e. the threads run in the same system on the same CPU.
In distributed computing there are also multiple tasks, but these can come from one job or possibly multiple jobs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Info</title>
      <link>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4391-distributed-systems-notes/info/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4391-distributed-systems-notes/info/</guid>
      <description>IN4391 Distributed Systems notes at TUDelft (Q3).
Studyguide: https://studiegids.tudelft.nl/a101_displayCourse.do?course_id=55274 Book: Andrew S. Tanenbaum, Maarten Van Steen, Distributed Systems, Principles and Paradigms (2nd Edition), Prentice Hall, 2006.
The content is based on the lecture material and summarized by myself, due to licensing no actual content of the course is copied here and any images and phrases used come from the book.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
