<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>IN4191 Notes on Nick Tehrany</title>
    <link>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4191-notes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in IN4191 Notes on Nick Tehrany</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4191-notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Lecture 5: Modern Stream Ciphers</title>
      <link>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4191-notes/lecture-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4191-notes/lecture-5/</guid>
      <description>Modern Stream Ciphers (Chapter 12) Encrypt bits rather than blocks as this is faster and easier to implement in hardware and software. Stream ciphers work by
\[c=m\oplus F_k(0)\]
and are IND-PASS secure if the PRF is secure.
Feedback shift registers are a standard way of producing a binary stream of data. These consist of a number of memory cells, where some of them are tapped that feed a feedback function. Registers are shifted down and the result from the feedback is shifted to the empty cell.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lecture 4: Defining Security</title>
      <link>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4191-notes/lecture-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4191-notes/lecture-4/</guid>
      <description>Security Games (Chapter 2.2) Security games are used to define security for cryptographic components, which contain an adversary and a challenger, and the idea is that the adversary needs to reach a certain objective given data provided by the challenger. These are typically represented visually with the adversary in a box and the challenger outside with the date it provides. The advantage of an adversary \(A\) is defined as a function bounded by time \(t\) that the adversary spends to try to solve the problem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lecture 3: Information Theoretic Security</title>
      <link>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4191-notes/lecture-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4191-notes/lecture-3/</guid>
      <description>Information Theoretic Security (Chapter 9) A crypto system is said to be computationally secure if the beset possible algorithm for breaking it requires \(N\) operations, where \(N\) is some large number above \(2^{128}\). It is impossible to prove that a system is computationally secure, as we do not know if there is a better algorithm for breaking it, hence a system is called secure if the best known algorithm requires a large number of computations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lecture 2: Classical Systems</title>
      <link>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4191-notes/lecture-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4191-notes/lecture-2/</guid>
      <description>Classical Systems (Chapter 7) An encryption algoithm or ciper is the transformation of plaintext to ciphertext with a secret key, depicted as
\[c=e_k(m)\]
with \(m\) being the plaintext,
\(e\) being the cipher function,
\(k\) being the secret key,
\(c\) being the ciphertext
The reverse process is called decryption or decipherment, depicted as
\[m=d_k(c)\]
The key above needs to be known to both parties, but must be kept secret from all others.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lecture 1: Introduction</title>
      <link>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4191-notes/lecture-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4191-notes/lecture-1/</guid>
      <description>What is Security? Security means:
Confidentiality: Access to systems or dataa is limited to authorised parties.
Integrity: WHen you receive data, you get the &amp;quot;right&amp;quot; data.
Availability: The system or data is there when you want it.
Objectives of Cryptography - Message authentication: valid message? - Data origin authentication: valid sender? - Enitity authentication: authenticate each other for communication  Kerkhoff&#39;s principle: The adversary knows all details about the crypto system except the private key.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Info</title>
      <link>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4191-notes/info/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nicktehrany.github.io/in4191-notes/info/</guid>
      <description>IN4191 Security and Cryptography notes at TUDelft (Q1).
Studyguide: https://studiegids.tudelft.nl/a101_displayCourse.do?course_id=55221
Book: Nigel P. Smart. 2015. Cryptography Made Simple (1st. ed.). Springer Publishing Company, Incorporated.
All content and images are based on and retrieved from the book and the lecture slides.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>